A Guide to the William Fleming Collection, 1773-1802
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg
William Fleming Collection, 1773-1802
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 96.12
14 items.
William Fleming.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 1996.
Biographical/Historical Information
William Fleming was born to John and Mary (Bolling) Fleming in Cumberland County, Va. Fleming studied law at the College of William and Mary and graduated in 1763. He held various political positions, including serving in the House of Burgesses and the House of Delegates, acting as a delegate to the Virginia Convention held in 1775-1776, and serving as a delegate from Cumberland County to the Continental Congress. In December 1788, Fleming received an appointment to the first Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals and served as a judge for this court until 1824.
Scope and Content Information
This collection includes several documents pertaining to Fleming's term as a Court of Appeals judge, such as notes on cases and Governor Beverley Randolph's official appointment of Fleming to the Court of Appeals. Financial and legal documents relating to Fleming's personal affairs are also present. They encompass receipts, bonds, accounts, and tax records. A list of taxable personal property includes the names of 46 slaves he owned.
In addition, a few documents are present which concern other individuals. They include a license for Robert Stanard to practice law, a writ for arrest, and a copy of a bill of chancery. These may be papers Fleming acquired in the course of operating his law practice.
Individuals mentioned in the documents include: John Banks; Thomas Blane; Thomas Bolling; Adam Craig; John Fleming; Thomas Fleming; William Fleming; Robert Gilliam; Daniel Mayo; William Mayo; Thomas Nelson; Beverley Randolph; Philip Sansum; Warner Servis; William Thomas; and John Wood.
Arrangement
Chronologically arranged.
Index Terms
Persons:
Bolling, Thomas.; Craig, Adam.; Fleming, John, d. 1767.; Fleming, Thomas.; Fleming, William, 1736-1824.; Gilliam, Robert.; Lewis, Warner, fl. 1796.; Lyons, Peter, 1734 or 5-1809.; Mayo, Daniel.; Mayo, William.; Nelson, Thomas, clerk of Gloucester County Court.; Pendleton, Edmund, 1721-1803.; Randolph, Beverley, 1754-1797.; Roane, Spencer, 1762-1822.; Sansum, Philip.; Servis, Warner.; Stanard, Robert, 1781-1846.; Wood, John, fl. 1797.
Subjects:
African Americans--Virginia--Chesterfield County.; Judges--Virginia.; Slaves--Virginia-- Chesterfield County.
Corporate Names:
Virginia. Supreme Court of Appeals.
Contents List
- Wrapper. Titled "Receipts: Col. R. Bolling."
- Wrapper. Titled "Papers relating to John Fleming's estate, who died 22 Apr 1767."
- Receipt, 17 March 1767.
  Thos. Bolling to Wm. Fleming.
- Bond, 1773.
  Robert Gilliam to Wm. Fleming.
- Inventory, 9 March 1787.
  William Fleming's taxable property in Chesterfield.
- Appointment, December 1788.
  William Fleming to the Court of Appeals, signed by Governor Beverley Randolph.
- Receipt, 7 May 1791.
  For wheat sold by William Fleming to William Lee, Manchester.
- Execution for debt, 18 June 1796.
  Signed by Thomas Nelson, clerk of the Gloucester County Court, relating to the lawsuit of Blanc (assignee of Young) v. Sansum and Warner Lewis.
- Draft, 20 July 1797.
  Drawn of Wm. Fleming by John Wood.
- Writ for arrest, 15 April 1801.
  Signed by Adam Craig.
- Notes, 1802.
  Written by Judge Fleming in response to Judge John Coalter's objections in the lawsuit Mayo v. Murchie, which concerned land in the City of Richmond.
- Law license of Robert Stanard, 26 October 1802.
  Signed by Edmund Pendleton, Peter Lyons, and Spencer Roane. Stanard became a judge for the Court of Appeals.
- Bill of chancery.
  Copy of pp.5-8 of a bill of chancery concerning the lawsuit of Cabbell v. Mayo, a dispute regarding land along the Fluvanna River.